# Chitralekha Gupta, Senior Research Fellow

Contact COM2-01-07, Augmented Human Lab, Information School of Computing, National University of Singapore

Google Scholar, Website, Github E-mail: chitralekha@nus.edu.sg

Research Interests My research interests lie at the intersection of deep learning, human-computer interaction, and audio, particularly in singing quality and lyrics analysis, controllability of audio generative models, explainability of AI, and audio-based assistive technologies.

Work EXPERIENCE

Senior Research Fellow

Mar 2023 - Present

Augmented Human Lab, School of Computing, NUS

Research Fellow

Augmented Human Lab, School of Computing, NUS (PI: Suranga Nanayakkara) 2022-2023 Communications and New Media, Faculty of Arts, NUS (PI: Lonce Wyse) 2021-2022 2019-2021 Human Language Technology lab, Electrical and Comp Engg., NUS (PI: Haizhou Li)

Co-Founder of MuSigPro Pte. Ltd.

Aug 2019 - Present

A music technology start-up that commercializes two AI-based music technologies developed during my PhD and post-doc - a singing quality assessment algorithm, and an audio-to-lyrics time aligner.

Research Engineer at Airbus Defense and Space, Bangalore March 2013 - July 2014 Aug 2011 - Feb 2013 Software Developer at Dell R&D, Bangalore

**EDUCATION** 

Ph.D. at Dept. of Computer Science,

2015 - 2019

National University of Singapore (NUS)

Thesis: Comprehensive evaluation of singing quality; Advisors: Haizhou Li and Ye Wang

Master of Technology at Dept. of Electrical Engg. 2008 - 2011 Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IIT-Bombay)

Thesis: Objective assessment of ornaments in Indian singing; Advisor: Preeti Rao

Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics Engg.

2004 - 2008

M.S. University, Baroda, India

SELECTED PROJECTS Through my experience as a research fellow and a senior research fellow, I have worked on a diverse range of projects related to audio and deep learning. A selected few of them are below:

- Music Analysis:
  - (a) Singing Quality Evaluation: I have worked on signal processing-based and machine learningbased explainable modeling of singing quality, based on pitch, rhythm, ornaments, as well as pronunciation.

12 papers published across ISMIR, Interspeech, APSIPA, IEEE/ACM TASLP 2017 - 2022

(b) Alignment and Recognition of Lyrics in Music: I have worked on kaldi-based modular ASR models for the task of lyrics-to-audio alignment and lyrics recognition. I have also co-authored works on espnet-based end-to-end ASR models lyrics recognition.

9 papers published across ICASSP, Interspeech, SMC, IEEE/ACM TASLP

2019 - 2022

- Controllability of Sound Synthesis using Generative Models: I have worked on exploring supervised and unsupervised methods of inducing control over certain attributes of synthesized audio by manipulating the latent space of Generative Adversarial Networks. 6 papers published across ICASSP, ISMIR, ACM IUI, Springer, IEEE/ACM TASLP 2021 - Present
- **Assistive Augmentation Technologies:**

I have worked with people with visual impairments to build an assistive tool that creates awareness of distant scenes through sonification, i.e. converting scene information into relevant sounds through generative models. Published in ACM IMWUT 2023 - Present

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- Chitralekha Gupta, Shreyas Sridhar, Denys Mattheis, Christophe Jouffrais, and Suranga Nanayakkara, Sonic Vista: Towards Creating Awareness of Distant Scenes through Sonification, IMWUT, 2024.
- Purnima Kamath, **Chitralekha Gupta**, Lonce Wyse, and Suranga Nanayakkara, *Example-Based Framework for Perceptually Guided Audio Texture Generation*, *IEEE/ACM TASLP*, 2024.
- Elliot Wen, Chitralekha Gupta, Prasanth Sasikumar, Mark Billinghurst, James Wilmott, Emily Skow, Arindam Dey, and Suranga Nanayakkara, VR.net: A Real-world Dataset for Virtual Reality Motion Sickness Research, IEEE VR, 2024 - Best Paper Award.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Purnima Kamath, Yize Wei, Zhuoyao Li, Suranga Nanayakkara, and Lonce Wyse, *Towards Controllable Audio Texture Morphing*, *ICASSP*, 2023.
- Xiaoxue Gao, Chitralekha Gupta, and Haizhou Li, PoLyScriber: Integrated Training of Extractor and Lyrics Transcriber for Polyphonic Music, IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2023.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Masataka Goto, Deep Learning Approaches in Topics of Singing Information Processing (Overview Paper), IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2022.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Yize Wei, Purnima Kamath, Zhuoyao Li, and Lonce Wyse, *Parameter Sensitivity of Deep-Feature based Evaluation Metrics for Audio Textures, ISMIR*, 2022.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Emre Yılmaz, and Haizhou Li, Automatic Lyrics Alignment and Transcription in Polyphonic Music: Does Background Music Help?, ICASSP, 2020.
- Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Ye Wang, Automatic Leaderboard: Evaluation of Singing Quality without a Standard Reference, IEEE/ACM TASLP, 2019.

### SELECTED ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

- DCASE Challenge 2023: Our generative model system for the Foley Sound Synthesis Task at this international challenge ranked 3rd amongst 26 submitted systems.
- MIREX 2020 and 2019: Our "Automatic Lyrics-to-Audio Alignment and Lyrics Transcription" system ranked 1st in the International Music Information Retrieval Evaluation eXchange platform for two consecutive years 2019 and 2020. (Press Release)
- NUS Graduate Research Innovation Program (GRIP) Award, July 2019, a start-up grant for MuSigPro Pte. Ltd.

# PATENT (PENDING)

Chitralekha Gupta, Haizhou Li, and Ye Wang, "System and Method for Assessing Quality of A Singing Voice"; U.S. Patent Application No. 17/631,646 filed on 8 February 2022.

#### INVITED TALKS

- Invited talk at Meta ARIA Summit, Redmond WA, USA 2024.
- Invited talk at Music Research Symposium, Singapore 2023.
- Women in MIR panelist at ISMIR 2022.

### Overseas/ Industry Collaborators

• CNRS, Toulouse, France (Dr. Christophe Jouffrais)

2023 - Present

• Meta Platforms Inc. (META)

2022 - Present

• AIST, Japan (Dr. Masataka Goto)

2021 - 2022

#### MENTORSHIP

- Mentored 2 PhD Students, and Co-supervised 2 Masters students.
- Served as a PhD Thesis Examiner of a student from Sorbonne University, Paris in 2023.

## RESEARCH COMMUNITY SERVICE

- Reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Multimedia, IEEE/ACM Transactions of Audio, Speech and Language Processing, ISMIR, ICASSP, Interspeech, ICME, APSIPA Transactions, Springer International Journal of Social Robotics, IEEE Access, Springer Multimedia Systems Journal.
- Organizing Committee Member: ISMIR 2017, ASRU 2019, SIGDIAL 2021, ICASSP 2022, ISMIR 2022, AH Workshop 2023.